Our text is focusing
on the powerful effect
今日の聖句から 正しい仕方で
心をこめて祈るなら—
that prayer can have on us
when it is true prayer,
エホバは力を与えてくださることが
分かります
genuine prayer.
Mere communication with God
祈りとは言えない
神とのコミュニケーションもあります
is not necessarily prayer.
In Genesis
chapters 3 and 4,
創世記 3章と4章で アダムは
罪を犯した後 エホバと会話しました
after Adam had sinned,
he had dialogue with Jehovah,
but it could hardly
be viewed as prayer.
でも それは祈りとはとても言えません
どうしてでしょうか？
Why?
Because prayer involves trust,
祈るためには
信頼や敬意 謙遜な態度—
respect, humility, devotion,
そして 相手に献身し
頼り切っていることが必要だからです
and a sense of dependence
on the one to whom
the prayer is directed.
Now, just to highlight
the importance of trust
では 信頼の大切さ 祈りを通して
与えられる助けについて考えましょう
and prayer’s effectiveness,
let’s open our Bibles
to Psalm 91,
聖書の詩編 91編をお開きください
and we’ll see the important quality
of trust highlighted.
この聖句から
信頼の大切さが分かります
Psalm 91,
we’ll read verses 1 and 2.
詩編 91編1, 2節です
“Anyone dwelling in the secret place
of the Most High
“至高者の秘められた所に住む者は—”
“自ら全能者の陰に
宿り場を得ることになる”
will lodge under the shadow
of the Almighty.”
Well, we notice “the secret place,”
“秘められた所”
そこにいれば安全です
a place of spiritual security
だれも ほかのどんなものも
この場所にいる人から—
where no one or no thing
can rob us of our faith in Jehovah
エホバへの愛や信仰を
奪うことはできません
or our love for Jehovah.
And it’s secret because unbelievers
can’t understand it.
またそこは 信じない人には
理解できない秘密の場所です
But now,
how do we get there?
では そこに入るには
どうしたらよいでしょうか？
Verse 2:
“I will say to Jehovah:
2節です
“わたしはエホバに申し上げよう”
‘You are my refuge
and my stronghold,
“「あなたはわたしの避難所
わたしのとりで—”
my God in whom I trust.’”
“わたしの依り頼む
わたしの神です」と”
So the key of getting
into the secret place,
この気持ちです
秘められた所に入る
つまり神の平和を得るには—
the key to getting
the peace of God,
is this humility
and trust in Jehovah.
謙遜になり
エホバを信頼する必要があるのです
And we notice
the expression here:
そして “あなたはわたしの避難所
わたしのとりで”とあります
“You are my refuge
and my stronghold.”
In this context, not ours
—while it’s true—
エホバはわたしたちみんなの
避難所ですが—
but it has to be personal.
大切なのは エホバを
自分個人の避難所とすることなのです
And that’s the trust
that we have on an individual basis.
And how grateful we are
that we have Jehovah’s listening ear,
エホバは耳を向けて
話を聴いてくださいます
and he hears us
ダビデもそのことについて語りました
because of something
that David said.
We go to Psalm 69 this time,
今度は詩編 69編に移りましょう
and as we turn here,
we’d like to ask you to think,
完全に一致はしなくても—
“Have you ever felt,
to a reasonable degree,
ここでダビデが言っているような気持ち
になったことがあるでしょうか？
the same way that David
expresses himself here?”
ダビデはこの時 大きなストレスで
もうだめだと感じていました
He’s going through
a very stressful time, overwhelmed,
and in verse 20 of Psalm 69,
he says:
詩編 69編20節でこう述べています
“Reproach has broken my heart,
“そしりがわたしの心を破りました
その傷は治りません”
“and the wound is incurable.
“I was hoping for sympathy,
but there was none,
“そして わたしは同情を示してくれる者を
待ち望みましたが—”
and for comforters,
but I found none.”
“だれもいませんでした”
So at times,
our fellow believers
兄弟姉妹も家族も親友も
頼りにできないことがあります
—our family members even,
close friends—
they may not be able to help us
the way we need to be helped.
どうしてでしょうか？
And why is that?
自分のことで精いっぱい
なのかもしれません
Well, for one thing, they may be
very busy dealing with their own problems,
また ストレスの原因は
人によって違い—
and they don’t have
the time to really notice.
ある人にはストレスになることを
別の人は全く気にしないかもしれません
Or the other factor is
that we all have things that differ
when it comes to causing us stress.
What is a real stress for one person
is not so hard for another.
もし たいしたことではないのにと
思いながら—
問題に対処しようと闘っている人を
見ているだけだとしたら—
And if they look on
and see someone
going through something
that they find easy,
もっと同情心が必要でしょう
perhaps the sympathy will be lacking.
But, nonetheless,
verse 33 of this same Psalm says:
しかし 69編33節にはこうあります
“For Jehovah
is listening to the poor,
“エホバは貧しい者たちの言葉を
聴いておられ—”
and he will not despise
his captive people.”
“ご自分の捕らわれ人を
決してさげすまれない”
Now, in principle,
sometimes we may feel captive
何かに捕らわれてしまうことがあります
to our circumstances
自分の状況とか気持ちとか
強い感情とかが問題で—
or to the feelings
that we’re experiencing,
to our emotions,
to what we are going through
身動きできなくなってしまうのです
—we feel trapped.
Other people may not understand
だれにも分かってもらえない—
助けてくれる人がいない
ということもあります
or may not be able to help us.
But notice the reassurance
そういう時には
歴代第二 6章29, 30節から力を得られます
in 2 Chronicles 6:29, 30.
This is the prayer of Solomon
神殿を献堂した時のソロモンの祈りです
at the time
of the dedication of the temple.
And in 2 Chronicles 6:29
he says:
歴代第二 6章29節には—
“だれでも あるいはあなたの民
イスラエルが皆—”
“Whatever request for favor
“may be made by any man
“各々自分の災厄や痛みを知るゆえに
彼らの側でどんな祈り—”
“or by all your people Israel
“(for each one knows
“his own plague and his own pain)
“恵みを求めるどんな願いがあっても”
とあります
when they spread out
their hands toward this house,”
必要はそれぞれです
so we’re unique.
では 助けられる人がいないのは
どうしてでしょうか？30節
Other people may not be able to do it.
Why?
Verse 30:
“Then may you hear
from the heavens,
“あなたが天からお聞きになり
そして許し—”
“your dwelling place,
and may you forgive;
“各々にそのすべての道にしたがって
お与えください”
“and reward each one
according to all his ways,
“あなたはその心をご存じだからです”
“for you know his heart
“(you alone truly know
“（ただあなただけが 人間の子の心を
よく知っておられるのです）”
the human heart).”
So even if our friends care,
それで 気にかけて助けたいと
思ってくれている友人でも—
even if they want to be helpful,
they cannot possibly see
the depth of what we’re feeling
あなたの気持ちや考えや受けている影響
全部を理解できないことがあるのです
or what we’re thinking
or how it’s affecting us,
but Jehovah does.
でも エホバは分かっています
He sees right
to the heart of the matter,
本当のことを知っておられます
and how reassuring that is.
安心して良いのです
So we trust him
because he really knows us.
すべてを知っておられるエホバを
信頼しましょう
But there’s something else
involved in this trust.
エホバへの信頼を表わせる
別の分野があります
Matthew 6:33 says:
マタイ 6章33節にはこうあります
“Keep on, then, seeking first
the Kingdom and his righteousness,
“ですから 王国と神の義を
いつも第一に求めなさい”
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
“そうすれば これらほかのものはみな
あなた方に加えられるのです”
Now, there’s personal trust
—trust that Jehovah
knows what I need
エホバはわたしの必要を知っている—
and that he’s going to,
as he always has, provide it.
これまでいつも必要なものを
与えてくださった—
今度も与えてくださると
信じることです
But there can be a pitfall.
If a person
is naturally calm, confident,
ある人は冷静で自信があって
もしかしたら才能もあって—
perhaps has a natural ability,
family history that’s rich
感情面で満たされていて
財産も相続しています
—both emotionally,
maybe even financially—
all of these things
can make a person begin to feel,
そしてこう考えます
“エホバを信頼している
だけどこれは自分でできる”
‘Yes, I trust in Jehovah,
but I can do this myself.’
You know, sometimes
we may hear this expression
周りの人もそう言うかもしれません
when we hear of someone
例えば だれかが特別全時間奉仕から
正規開拓に移る—
that’s being transitioned
from one form of special service,
perhaps into
the regular pioneer work
or they have to leave Bethel
for good reasons,
あるいは ベテルを出て世俗の仕事に
就くときなど こう言います
and they have to go back
and get some secular work.
Have you ever heard this?
“あの人は手に職があるから大丈夫だ”
“They’re going to do fine
because they have marketable skills.”
もちろん 技術があるのは良いことです
王国のために働いて
それを身に着けてきたかもしれません
Now,
that’s a good thing.
Perhaps those marketable skills
have been developed
in pursuing Kingdom interests,
and that’s fine.
でも 技術があるから
大丈夫なのでしょうか？
But we have to be careful.
それとも 王国を第一にし—
Will they be fine
because of their skills
エホバが世話しておられるから
大丈夫なのでしょうか？
or because of their continuing
to seek first the Kingdom
“あの人は大丈夫 手に職があるから”
と言う場合 こう考えてください
and they let Jehovah
be the one that provides for them?
And we’ll have to be careful too
when we use that expression
それがなかったら
どうなるでしょうか？
“They’ll have no problem;
they have marketable skills.”
それでもエホバは
世話してくださいます
What if someone doesn’t?
Well, Jehovah
takes care of them too.
アモスはアモス 7章14, 15節で
こう言いました
Amos 7:14, 15,
Amos said:
“わたしは預言者ではなく
預言者の子でもなかった”
‘I wasn’t a prophet
or the son of a prophet.
I was a nipper of figs,
a very lowly herdsman, shepherd.’
“わたしは牧夫であり エジプトいちじくの
実をはさむ者であった”
But Jehovah took him,
used him, and provided for him.
エホバは 牧夫のアモスを選んで
用い 世話しました
So marketable skills
were not the key factor.
手に職があるかどうかは
重要ではありません
And so we keep that
in its proper perspective.
これを忘れないようにしましょう
And finally,
in imitation of Jehovah,
エホバに倣い 他の人を力づけ
問題に立ち向かうよう助けるため—
when we try to help people,
we want to use the most powerful tool
we have to encourage them
強力な道具を用いましょう
and to help them deal
with their anxiety.
There was an experience
in the February 15, 1988, Watchtower
「ものみの塔」
1988年2月15日号に—
about Brother Arthur Winkler.
アルトゥール･ウインクラー兄弟の
経験が出てきます
Now,
the Gestapo found him,
and they beat him
without mercy,
兄弟はゲシュタポに捕らえられ
容赦なく殴打されました
knocked out his teeth,
dislocated his jaw.
歯は折れ あごははずれて—
His whole body
was raw from the beating,
全身傷だらけの姿で
暗い牢獄に投げ込まれます
and they threw him in a dark cell.
At that moment,
Brother Winkler said,
こう言っています
“I was in desperate need
of spiritual food,
“霊的なものが本当に必要で
エホバに祈りました”
and I prayed to Jehovah.”
And then he talked to the guard
and asked him to help him.
看守に助けを求めると
扉が開き 聖書が投げ込まれます
The cell door opened
and a Bible was thrown in,
兄弟は “喜ばしい真理の言葉を読むのが
毎日の楽しみで 貴重な時間でした“
and he said:
“That daily enjoyment
of those pleasant words of truth
“were precious.
“霊的にますます強められてゆくのを
感じました”と言っています
I felt myself
getting stronger spiritually.”
So, then,
when we go to help people,
では だれかを助けたいと思うとき
何を持っていけば一番良いでしょうか？
the best thing we can do
in helping them cope is,
not with some
often-used phrase
よく使う言葉ではありません
or something that is
repeatable all the time,
聖書です
その人は 自分の状況という牢獄に
捕らえられたように感じているかもしれません
but make sure it is the Bible.
They may feel captive,
imprisoned by their situation.
しかし 聖書の記述 難しい時期を
乗り越えた人たちに関する記述以上に—
But an account from the Bible
—an account of a Bible character
力を与えるものはありません
that had gone through tough times
and came through—
those are the most meaningful things
to deal with it.
パウロはコリント第二 11章で—
自分が経験した試練を
思い返しています
Perhaps
2 Corinthians 11:23-31,
そして何年か後に 今日の
フィリピ 4章の聖句を書きました
where Paul reviewed
all of those things that he went through,
and yet years later,
he wrote our day’s text for today,
心の平安を保てるよう
エホバが助けてくださったのです
saying Jehovah helped him
stay calm and assisted him.
So may these reminders
from the Scriptures
今日考えた点が 個人として—
また 他の人を助ける上で
役立つことを願っています
help us to cope and help others
to cope with anxieties.